Register of the Ivan V. Emel'ianov Papers, 1908-1960
Hoover Institution Archives
Ivan V. Emel'ianov Papers
1908-1960
2000C22
Hoover Institution Archives
14 microfilm reels (2.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Russian agricultural cooperative movement and to the theory of economic cooperation. Includes papers of Nataliia V. Emel'ianova, chemist and wife of I. V. Emel'ianov.
Emel'ianov, Ivan V., 1880-1945
Access
Collection open for research.
Biography
A prominent specialist in the field of cooperative economic theory, I. V. Emel'ianov was born at Uspenskii zavod, Tobol'skaia guberniia, on 1 November 1880 (O. S.). In 1900, he graduated from Tobol'sk seminary, but decided to continue his education in the field of agronomy. In 1907 he graduated from Kiev Polytechnic Institute with a degree in that subject, proceeding to work as an agronomist for local zemstvo organizations. From 1910 to 1912 he served as agricultural agent for the Ekaterinoslavskoe zemstvo in the United States. Following his return to Russia, most of his career was spent in various capacities in the Khar'kov region, where he worked closely with cooperative organizations.
In 1917, he was elected a member of the Khar'kov gubernskaia zemskaia uprava and Chairman of the Board of the Khar'kov Zemstvo Bureau of Small Credit. In September 1919 under the White regime he was appointed chairman of the Khar'kov gubernskaia zemskaia uprava. The same year, he became an officer of the Selosoyus cooperative and Moscow Narodny Bank. Arriving in Prague in 1921, he proceeded to help found the Russkii institut sel'sko-khoziaistvennoi kooperatsii (of which he was deputy director until 1927) and established the journals Zemledelie and Khutor, which he edited.
Emigrating to the United States at the invitation of Rutgers University, he taught there until 1933, thereafter working for various government agencies as an economist. His Ph. D. thesis at Columbia, Economic Theory of Cooperation was completed in 1942, only some three years before his death in Washington, D.C. on 17 December 1945.
Biographiccal Note: Ivan V. Emel'ianov
1880 November 1 (O.S.) Born, Uspenskii Zavod, Tobol'sk guberniia, Russia
1900 Graduated, Tobol'sk Seminary
1907 Graduated, Kiev Polytechnic Institute
1910-1912 Agricultural Agent of the Ekaterinoslavskoe zemstvo in the United States
1912 Appointed agronomist for Khar'kovskoe gubernskoe zemstvo
1913 February 6 Married Nataliia Osviatinskaia
1917 Elected member of the Kar'kovskaia zemskaia uprava and appointed Chairman of the Board of the Khar'kov zemstvo Bureau of Small Credit
1919 September Appointed director of the Khar'kovsakaia zemskaia uprava
1919-1921 Member, Board of directors, Selosoyus, Limited and Moskovskii Narodnyi Bank (also their representative abroad)
1921 Arrived, Prague, Czechoslovakia Editor, Zemledelie
1921-1927 Professor of economics and Vice-Director, Russkii Institut sel'sko-khoziaistvennoi kooperatsii, Prague
1922 Editor, Khutor
1923 Magister of Agronomy (Agricultural economics), Department of Natural and Agricultural Sciences, Russkaia akademicheskaia gruppa v Prage Author, Kooperativnyia organizatsii sredi zemlediel'tsev
1927 Emigrated to the United States
1927-1933 Professor, Rutgers University
1933-1939 Economist, various positions, National Recovery Administration, Department of Labor, National Economic Committee
1940-1945 Economic Analyst, U.S. Bureau of the Census
1942 Ph.D., Economics, Columbia University Author, Economic Theory of Cooperation
1945 December 17 Died, Washington, D.C.
Biographiccal Note: Nataliia V. Emel'ianova
1890 August 26 (O.S.) Born, Khar'kov, Russia (née Nataliia Osviatinskaia)
1913 February 6 Married Ivan V. Emel'ianov, Khar'kov
1919 Graduated, Khar'kov University
1921 May Arrived, Prague, Czechoslovakia
1925 Ph.D. (Dr. of Natural Sciences), Chemistry, Charles University, Prague Author, Researches with the Dropping Mercury Cathode: Nickel and Cobalt
1925-1927 Research Assistant, Charles University
1927 Arrived, New York
1928 Author (with J. Heyrovský), Maxima on Current Voltage Curves
1929-1932 Research Assistant, Laboratory of Experimental Therapeutics, Cornell University
1940-1961 Russian language teacher, Washington, D.C., Berlitz School of Languages, CIA, and Trinity College)
1948 March 25 Elected active member, New York Academy of Sciences
1965 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of the noted theoretician of cooperative economics, Ivan V. Emel'ianov. Most of the collection consists of his writings on cooperative issues and correspondence relating to his scholarly and social activities while in Czechoslovakia (1921-1927) and the United States (1927-1945). Special mention should be made of the correspondence and research material for his dissertation, subsequently published as The Economic Theory of Cooperation. Correspondence and subject file material also illustrate his involvement in Russian émigré organizations of an educational and social character in both countries. There is also a set of documents pertaining to his activities during the Russian Civil War, when he represented cooperative organizations in Europe.
Many of Emel'ianov's publications are printed copies that include the entire issue of the periodicals they appeared in, which are very often themselves bibliographic rarities. A printed matter series, which includes a significant number of rare publications on cooperative issues by other authors, supplements Emel'ianov's own work in this field.
His wife, Nataliia Emel'ianova, was a chemist by profession, and the collection contains a number of her scientific publications, as well as biographical information and correspondence detailing her involvement in émigré life.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials and copyright to them (with some exceptions) are the property of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Agriculture--Russia.; Chemistry.; Cooperative societies--Russia.; Cooperative societies.; Czechoslovakia.; Russia.; Russians--Czechoslovakia.; Russians--United States.; Soviet Union.; United States.
- IVAN V. EMEL'IANOV, 1915-1951.; Boxes 1-11
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical file includes biography by his wife, Nataliia, and educational, employment, family and other records, arranged by physical form. Correspondence file arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Speeches and writings arranged chronologically by title. Academic and Civil service career files include material arranged alphabetically by, respectively, name of academic institution and physical form. Subject files arranged alphabetically by subject heading (includes correspondence and writings). Printed matter file consists of writings by others arranged alphabetically, mainly relating to topics in agriculture and agricultural cooperation
- NATALIIA V. EMEL'IANOVA, 1908-1960.; Boxes 12-13
  Biographical file includes clippings, curricula, educational and employment records arranged by physical form. Correspondence file arranged by name of correspondent. Writings arranged chronologically by title
- PHOTOGRAPHS, c. 1921-1940s., Box 14
  Include numerous photographs of the Emel'ianovs, together and separately, and of various individuals and places associated with their life
- Ivan V. Emel'Ianov, 1915-1951
  - Biographical file, See also Speeches and writings/General/Scrapbooks, 1919-1946.
    - Biography, written by Nataliia V. Emel'ianova (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Certificates. Includes copy of certificate appointing Emel'ianov director of Khar'kovskaia gubernskaia zemskaia uprava, 1919 September 4 (Folder 2)
    - Clippings about Emel'ianov (Folder 3)
    - Curriculum vitae (Folder 4)
    - Diplomas (Folder 5)
    - Employment records (Civil service)
      - Application forms and ratings (Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1933-1941 (Folder 7)
    - Family correspondence
      - Emel'ianova, Nataliia V., 1928-1934 and undated (Folder 8)
      - Emel'ianov, Nikolai V. [brother], 1930 (Folder 9)
    - Letters of recommendation, Includes letter from Pitirim Sorokin, 1927-1938. (Folder 10)
    - Membership cards (Russian War Veterans, Inc.), 1934-1942 (Folder 11)
    - Powers of attorney. Includes excerpt from minutes of meeting of Vserossiiskii zemskii soiuz, authorizing Emel'ianov to act as purchasing controller for Balkan operations, 1919 December 10 (Folder 12)
    - Miscellany. Includes Emel'ianov's sketch of his place of birth, various financial and real estate documents, business cards (Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, See also Biographical file and Academic career file. Includes letters addressed to both Emel'ianov and his wife, but see also NATALIIA V. EMEL'IANOVA/Correspondence, for other letters addressed to both of them, 1915-1951.
    - General
      - General, 1931-1939 (Folder 14)
      - Acknowledgements, 1923-1941 (Folder 15)
      - Congratulations, 1924-1930 and undated (Folder 16)
      - Invitations, 1923-1938 (Folder 17)
      - Requests, 1922-1941 (Folder 18)
    - Unidentified, 1927-1932 (Folder 19)
    - Agger, E. E., 1931-1942 (Folder 20)
    - Alekseev, V., Includes correspondence with others regarding address of F. M. Dostoevsky's granddaughter, 1931. (Folder 21)
    - Allen, J. Sandeman, [1926]-1927 (Folder 22)
    - Alpaugh, J. Everett, 1933-1934 (Folder 23)
    - Antsyferov, Aleksei Nikolaevich, 1927 (Folder 24)
    - Backer, Jacob, 1936-1937 (Folder 25)
    - Bel'govskii, K., 1927 (Folder 26)
    - Bilimovich, Aleksandr, 1934-1936 and undated (Folder 27)
    - Borodin, D., 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bothezat, George de, 1931 (Folder 2)
    - Brasol, Boris, 1933-1939 (Folder 3)
    - Brdlík, V., 1930 (Folder 4)
    - Brunst, Viktor Emil'evich, 1920-1931 (Folder 5)
    - Burns, Arthur F., 1939-1942 and undated (Folder 6)
    - Chavchavadze, Pavel A., Prince, Includes correspondence with others, 1933. (Folder 7)
    - Chechetkin, Aleksei Pavlovich, 1931 (Folder 8)
    - Chernikov, I. I., 1931-1933 (Folder 9)
    - Clark, Lincoln, 1944 (Folder 10)
    - Clothier, Robert, 1932-1933 (Folder 11)
    - Coulter, John Lee, 1927-1934 (Folder 12)
    - Crystal, Herman, 1934 (Folder 13)
    - Danilevskii, V. V., 1928 (Folder 14)
    - Demosfenov, S. S., n.d. (Folder 15)
    - Deriaba, Petr Alekseevich, 1932-1933 (Folder 16)
    - Dolgopiatov, G. I., 1927-1934 (Folder 17)
    - Dolgorukov, P., Prince, 1936 (Folder 18)
    - Elsworth, R. H., 1943 (Folder 19)
    - Epanchin, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1938 (Folder 20)
    - Evglevskii. See Sky, B. P.
    - Fedorov, Mikhail, 1928-1933 (Folder 21)
    - Fekula, Paul M., n.d. (Folder 22)
    - Fenin, Aleksandr Ivanovich, 1939 (Folder 23)
    - Filippovskii, Vasil' Osipovich, 1926 (Folder 24)
    - Fisher, Irving, 1929-1934 (Folder 25)
    - Fund for the Relief of Men of Letters and Science of Russia, 1933-1935 and undated (Folder 26)
    - Georgievskii, P., 1927-1937 and undated (Folder 27)
    - Gibson, Joseph W., 1933-1940 (Folder 28)
    - Gnedich, D. D., 1933-1937 (Folder 29)
    - Goodrich, Carter, 1932-1938 (Folder 30)
    - Goppen (Hoppen), Petr, 1933 (Folder 31)
    - [Grimm, David Davidovich], 1926 (Folder 32)
    - Gume (?), N., 1928 (Folder 33)
    - Gunderson, William E. (Folder 34)
    - Hodzha, Milan, 1936 (Folder 35)
    - Howard, Leland O., 1930 (Folder 36)
    - Howe, Charles B., 1931-1933 (Folder 37)
    - Kalishevskii, A. I., 1933-1934 (Folder 38)
    - Karinskii, N. S., Includes latter's correspondence with V. Shul'tse, 1932-1933. (Folder 39)
    - Karpovich, M. M., 1930-1931 (Folder 40)
    - Kay, Leo N., 1933-1940 and undated (Folder 41)
    - Kazakov, Viktor Nikolaevich, 1932 (Folder 42)
    - Kazarinov, Valerian V., 1923 (Folder 43)
    - Klindera, Ferdinand, 1936 (Folder 44)
    - Kolesnikov, V,., 1933 (Folder 45)
    - Kolesov, F., 1925-1938 (Folder 46)
    - Kolokol'tsov, V., 1922-1924 (Folder 47)
    - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich. See Russkoe sel'sko-khoziaistvennoe obshchestvo
    - Koropachinskii, P., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Kosinskii, Vladimir Andreevich, 1921-1938 (Folder 2)
    - Kukulevskii, Aleksandr, Rev., 1933-1938 (Folder 3)
    - Kukulevskii (?), Evstafii Leont'evich, 1931-1935 (Folder 4)
    - Leont'ev, M., 1938 (Folder 5)
    - Lipman, Jacob G., 1927-1937 (Folder 6)
    - Litviak, S., 1937 (Folder 7)
    - Lomshakov, A. S., 1929 (Folder 8)
    - Makletsov, A., 1927-1930 (Folder 9)
    - Marakuev, S., 1927-1928 (Folder 10)
    - Martynov, Zakhar, 1933 (Folder 11)
    - Mishtovt, I., 1935 (Folder 12)
    - Mokrzecki, S., 1931 (Folder 13)
    - Morgan, O. S., 1933-1941 (Folder 14)
    - Moskov, Evgenii A. [Moskoff, Eugene A.], 1930-1942 (Folder 15)
    - Nekrasov, Vladimir Alekseevich, 1940
    - Nevalonny [Nevialennyi], M., 1933-1938
    - Okulich, Iosif K., 1923-1942 (Folder 18)
    - OROVUZ. See Russian University League of America
    - Pechkovskii, M. I., Includes latter's correspondence with Jacob G. Lipman, A. I. Petrunkevitch, Pitirim Sorokin and others relating to the Emel'ianovs' emigration to the U.S. and the possibility of his obtaining academic employment, 1926-1941. (Folder 19)
    - Petrunkevitch, Alexander, 1931 (Folder 20)
    - Protopopov, Vladimir Aleksandrovich, 1930 (Folder 21)
    - Republican Party (N.Y.). State Committee, 1932-1933 (Folder 22)
    - Riabchikov, B. (?), 1922 (Folder 23)
    - Rozhdestvenskii, Aleksandr Pavlovich (Folder 24)
    - Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society of America, 1936 (Folder 25)
    - Russian University League of America (OROVUZ), 1933-1936 (Folder 26)
    - Russkoe sel'sko-khoziaistvennoe obshchestvo, Correspondence primarily with Petr Filaretovich Konstantinov and V. A. von Reimers, 1938-1942 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Savchenko, I., 1929-1930 (Folder 2)
    - Savinskii, V. N., 1931 (Folder 3)
    - Sergii, Bishop, 1933 and undated (Folder 4)
    - Service Bureau for Russians, 1928 (Folder 5)
    - Shebeko, N. N., 1939 (Folder 6)
    - Sheen, Fulton J., 1941 (Folder 7)
    - Shindler, Camille (Kamill Gavrilovich], 1928-1935 and undated (Folder 8)
    - Shvarts, Aleksandr Iosifovich, 1936 (Folder 9)
    - Sirotkin, Vasilii Vasil'evich, 1932 (Folder 10)
    - Sky (Evglevskii?), B. P., 1935 (Folder 11)
    - Snesarev, V., 1928 (Folder 12)
    - Sorokin, Pitirim, 1924-1927 (Folder 13)
    - Sorokin, S., 1934 (Folder 14)
    - Sosnovskii, P., 1929 (Folder 15)
    - Sporysh (?), L., 1934-1938 (Folder 16)
    - Stefanovskii, Stefan Mikhailovich, 1931 (Folder 17)
    - Struve, Petr Berngardovich, 1925 and undated (Folder 18)
    - Tereshchenko, Valerii Ivanovich, 1932-1940 (Folder 19)
    - Timoshenko, Stepan P., 1931 (Folder 20)
    - Timoshenko, V. P., 1940 (Folder 21)
    - Tsurikov, N. A., 1927-1933 (Folder 22)
    - Vasil'ev, V. V., 1931-1942 (Folder 23)
    - Vegner, A. Iu., 1921 (Folder 24)
    - Vernadsky, G. V., 1931 (Folder 25)
    - Vinnichuk, A. G., 1927 (Folder 26)
    - Vserossiiskii natsional'nyi krest'ianskii soiuz, 1931 (Folder 27)
    - Zavadskii, Sergei, 1926-1935 (Folder 28)
    - Zhitkov, I., 1928 (Folder 29)
  - Speeches and writings, See also Subject file/Agriculture, Cooperative/Letterbooks, 1921-1951.
    - General
      - Letters to the editor, Printed copies, 1931 and undated. (Folder 30)
      - Newspaper interviews and accounts of speeches, Printed copies. Includes correspondence related to speeches, 1929-1932 and undated. (Folder 31)
      - Notes, n.d. (Folder 32)
      - Scrapbooks, Include clippings of newspaper articles by and about Emel'ianov, photograph of him and articles by others on subjects related to Emel'ianov's interests, 1921-1946. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Agricultural Cooperatives in the United States," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - "Cooperative Associations Among Retailers," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - "Differences in Cooperative Pattern of Farmers' Cooperative Associations," Holograph (fragment), n.d. (Folder 4)
    - "Gospodin Gannibal," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 5)
    - "K voprosu ob organiatsii miestnago samoupravleniia na Donu," See Subject file/Agriculture, Cooperative/Letterbooks, n.d.
    - "P. I. Georgievskii," Typescript (incomplete), n.d. (Folder 6)
    - "Puti russkoi zemlediel'cheskoi kooperatsii," See Subject file/Agriculture, Cooperative/Letterbooks, n.d.
    - "Russkaia derevnia o sovietskoi shkole," Vozrozhdenie, Printed copy, n.d. (Folder 7)
    - "Russkie zemlediel'tsy v emigratsii," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - "The Silk Industry in New Jersey," Typescript (Folder 9)
    - Zemledielie, #1-4 (1921). Printed copy. Journal edited by Emel'ianov. Includes his editorials, reviews and two articles: "Grenzh," 1921 (#2) October and "Golos iz mogily," (#3-4), 1921 November-December (Folder 10)
    - Kooperativnyia organizatsii sredi zemlediel'tsev, 1923
      - Printed copy. Includes reviews pasted into book (Folder 11)
      - Miscellany. Includes reviews, abstract, congratulatory notes from Petr Struve, Iosif Okulich and others on the successful defense of the work as a dissertation (Folder 12)
    - "O prirodie kooperativnykh organiatsii sredi zemlediel'tsev," Kooperatsiia i sel'skoe khoziaistvo, Kniga I, Printed copy. Includes entire book, 1924. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "Kooperativnaia organizatsiia kak ob"edinenie khoziaistv," Kooperatsiia i sel'skoe khoziaistvo, Kniga II, Printed copy. Includes entire book (less cover and table of contents), 1924. (Folder 2)
    - Kooperativnaia organizatsiia kak ob"edinenie khoziaistv, Printed copy, 1924. (Folder 3)
    - Introduction to Jaroslav Cech, Naí zemedelkské inteligenci pro zemedelskou a druzstvení práci v Rusku, Printed copy (entire book), 1925. (Folder 4)
    - "Kooperativnoe ob"edinenie kak predpriiatie," Zapiski Russkago Instituta Sel'sko-Khoziaistvennoi Kooperatsii v Pragie, Kniga III, Printed copy (entire book), 1925. (Folder 5)
    - Kooperativnoe ob"edinenie kak predpriiatie, Printed copy. Includes clippings of reviews, 1925. (Folder 6)
    - "Kooperativnoe ob"edinenie i kartel'," and review of Kiyoshi Ogata, The Co-Operative Movement in Japan, Zapiski Russkago Instituta Sel'sko-Khoziaistvennoi Kooperatsii v Pragie, Kniga IV, Printed copy (entire book), 1926. (Folder 7)
    - Kooperativnoe ob"edinenie i kartel', Printed copy, 1926. (Folder 8)
    - "Zakonomiernosti v geograficheskom raspredielenii zemlediel'cheskago kooperativnago dvizheniia," Zapiski Russkago Instituta Sel'sko-Khoziaistvennoi Kooperatsii v Pragie, Kniga V, Printed copy (entire book), 1927. (Folder 9)
    - "Cooperatives," The Russian Student, Printed copy (entire issue), 1928 February. (Folder 10)
    - "Khuver i Smit," Vozrozhdenie, Printed copy, 1928 August 22. (Folder 11)
    - "Ptichka," Vozrozhdenie, Printed copy, 1928 September 19. (Folder 12)
    - "Pochemu russkie dolzhny golosovat' za Khuvera," Novoe russkoe slovo, Printed copy. Includes background material, 1928 October 28. (Folder 13)
    - "Teoreticheskaia postanovka kooperativnoi problemy (Teoriia kooperatsii)," Zapiski Russkago Instituta Sel'sko-Khoziaistvennoi Kooperatsii v Pragie, Kniga VI, Printed copy (entire book), 1929. (Folder 14)
    - "Sel'sko-khoziaistvennaia Rossiia i ee vozmozhnosti," Sovremennik, Printed copy (entire issue), 1929 May. (Folder 15)
    - Speech, untitled, broadcast over WHAP Radio, New York, 1929 November 22, and published in Russian in Khoziain, Typescript. Includes two drafts (Folder 16)
    - "Cooperation in Agriculture," A Systematic Sourcebook in Rural Sociology, vol. II, Typescript and printed copy (offprint), 1931. (Folder 17)
    - "Vybory prezidenta," Vozrozhdenie, Printed copy, 1932 February 22. (Folder 18)
    - "Associations Other than Trade Associations," [summary of a projected study], Typescript, 1939 March 24. (Folder 19)
    - Economic Theory of Cooperation, 1942
      - Background materials. Includes Charles B. Howe, Farmers' Cooperation in New Jersey, various government bulletins, reports and circulars, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, Includes letters to members of dissertation committee and university administration, as well as requests for the book and letters congratulating Emel'ianov on its publication. See also Correspondence/ Agger, E. E., Goodrich, Carter, and Morgan, O. S., 1933-1951. (Folder 2)
      - Comments by members of dissertation committee and faculty, 1939-1940
        - Brissenden, Paul F. (Folder 3)
        - Clark, J. M. (Folder 4)
        - Morgan, O. S. (Folder 5)
      - Drafts and notes (Folder 6)
      - Typescript
  - Academic career file, 1922-1942. See also Biographical file/Certificates, Curriculum vitae, Diplomas and Letters of Recommendation, as well as Correspondence/Pechkovskii, Mikhail, and Speeches and writings/ Kooperativnyia organizatsii sredi zemlediel'tsev, 1923, and Economic Theory of Cooperation
    - General
      - Correspondence and materials relating to applications for teaching posts (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - List of courses and examinations taken at University of Derpt (Iur'ev), Kiev Polytechnic Institute, 1904-1907, and Russkii institut sel'sko-khoziaistvennykh nauk, 1923, 1900-1904 (Folder 2)
    - Russkii institut sel'sko-khoziaistvennykh nauk, 1922-1923
      - Notebooks (Folder 3)
      - Examination books (Folder 4)
    - Rutgers University, Course materials, including examination forms, syllabi, reading lists and notes for courses entitled "Evolution of Economic Forms," "Agricultural Co-Operation" and "Marketing of Farm Products", 1927-1933. (Folder 5)
    - Columbia University, 1932-1942
      - General. Registration materials (Folder 6)
      - Examinations and graded works. Consist mainly of graphs and spreadsheets showing economic indicators (Folder 7)
      - Miscellany. Includes lecture notes, syllabi and reading lists (Folder 8)
  - Civil service career file, May include materials not authored by Emel'ianov or only partly authored by him, 1933-1945.
    - Memoranda, 1938-1942 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Reports
      - "On Deconcentration of Economic Mobilization for Defense," Typescript (Folder 2)
      - "Brief Preliminary Survey of Industrial Control and Recovery Measures in Great Britain, Germany, Italy and France," Typescript, 1935 March. (Folder 3)
      - "Textile Industry in the United Kingdom, France, Germany, Italy and Japan," Typescript. Includes draft and related material, 1936 February. (Folder 4)
      - "Evaluation of Reliability of Data on Income Classes of $5,000 and Over in Chicago," Typescript. Includes drafts and supplementary materials, 1937 October 15. (Folder 5)
      - "Work of the Bureau of the Census for National Defense and War Needs," Typescript, [1942]. (Folder 6)
      - "On Coverage of the Survey PD-275," Typescript. Includes notes and draft, 1942 April 16. (Folder 7)
      - "Standard Industrial Classification," Volume I, Mimeograph, 1945 June.
        - Revised second draft (Folder 8)
        - Final draft (Folder 9)
    - Miscellany. Notes and printed matter (Folder 10)
  - Subject file, 1920-1941
    - Agriculture, Cooperative--"Selosoyus" and "Sel'skosoiuz." Includes materials relating to the above organizations and Moskovsky Narodny Bank, collected or produced in the course of Emel'ianov's duties as representative of these organizations abroad, 1920-1922
      - Charters (Box 10, Folder 1)